Lou Erickson Papers
Lou Erickson Papers
1932-1967
1956-1967
Erickson, Lou B. (Louis Bernard), 1913-1990.
2.3 linear ft.
Original editorial cartoons, drawings, correspondence, published material, photos and personal calendars.
2651116
Biographical History
Louis Bernard Erickson (1913-1990), or Lou Erickson, was an American editorial cartoonist and illustrator.
Louis Bernard Erickson was born on December 27, 1913 in Marcus, Washington. While in school, Erickson drew illustrations and cartoons for his teachers about the subjects he had to study. From 1934 to 1935 he took classes at Wentworth College in Spokane before joining the Civilian Conservation Corps to fight forest fires. During his time with the CCC he edited and illustrated a CCC newspaper called the Microphone.
Erickson enlisted in the Army Air Corps and achieved the rank of staff sergeant during his service in WWII. During the war he drew the Separate Rations comic strip for Army Times. Erickson worked in public relations in Dallas, Texas following the war.
On July 17, 1950, Erickson jointed the Atlanta Journal as an artist in the advertising department. In December 1952, he transferred to the art staff of the news department and became the editorial page cartoonist on October 16, 1961. He also wrote columns and the occasional editorial piece and illustrated various parts of the newspaper including feature stories and the travel section. He also created the Sunday Funtime page.
Erickson was a prolific cartoonist whose work appeared in a variety of forms and depicted subjects beyond politics. In addition to his regular assignments for the Atlanta Journal he also drew freelance cartoons. Erickson collaborated with the Atlanta Traffic and Safety Council and produced materials used to educate the public about safe driving. Erickson illustrated several books and published a book of editorial cartoons in 1968, This is Maddox Country. He also wrote a humor book, It Takes One to Know One about Democrats and Republicans which was published in 1976. Textbook publishers used Erickson’s cartoons to illustrate works on history, economics and political science.
Many awards were presented to Erickson. Erickson was named “Man of the Year” for 1960 by the Georgia State Chamber of Commerce and received the Sigma Delta Chi Award for a series of cartoons in 1964. The Georgia Educational Association presented him with the School Bell Award for the contributions his editorial cartoons made to education. The Freedom Foundation George Washington Award was given to him in 1967 and his cartoons won him an award at the International Salon of Cartoons at Expo 67 in Montreal.
Erickson retired from the Atlanta Journal on December 31, 1982. Following a stroke and several weeks in a coma, Lou Erickson died of a heart attack April 15, 1990 at Northside Hospital in Atlanta.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Lou Erickson Papers are divided into 5 series: Cartoons, Biographical Material, Correspondence, Published Material, and Miscellaneous Drawings.
The Cartoons series contains approximately 131 original, undated editorial cartoons composed for the Atlanta Journal during the 1960s. Of particular interest are his cartoons depicting Georgia politics. Most have captions. The cartoons vary in size and were drawn primarily with brush, ink and graphite. Dimensions vary. Erickson signed his cartoons as "Eric".
Two personal calendars kept by Erickson can be found in the Biographical Material series. Erickson recorded details about his work day, monetary transactions as well as personal thoughts. Also in this series are over thirty photographs dating from 1932-1966. The earliest are high school class photos. Also included are photographs of Erickson during his service in WWII and at work. Five are in color, the majority are undated.
The collection also includes typed business Correspondence (1956-1966) sent to Erickson. Of particular note is a signed letter from Barry Goldwater. A variety of examples of Erickson's work as a cartoonist and a writer as early as the 1930s and 1940s can be found in the Printed Material series. Finally a few ink drawings and photocopies of drawings appear in the Miscellaneous Drawings series.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Separated Material
Two published books have been removed from this collection and sent to Rare Books. They are: Atlanta Street Scenes: Best of 10,000 by Hugh Park with illustrations by Lou Erickson (1954) and No Laughing Matter: The Cartoonist Focuses on Air Pollution published by the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare in 1966 featuring 60 cartoons about pollution by dozens of cartoonists, including two by Lou Erickson.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Erickson, Lou B. (Louis Bernard), 1913-1990.; Atlanta journal-constitution.; United States. Congress -- Caricatures and cartoons.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Editorial cartoons -- Georgia.; Editorial cartoons -- United States.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Maddox, Lester, 1915-2003 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Political cartoons.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; World politics -- 1945-1989 -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Appointment books.; Cartoons (humorous images); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Editorial cartoons.; Editorials.; Newspaper columns.; Promotional materials.; Photographs.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Lou Erickson, 1967.
Inventory
- Cartoons
  See below for an index to the cartoons.
  - Cartoons without captions (Oversize 1, Folder 1)
  - Captions A-B (Oversize 1, Folder 2)
  - Captions C-D (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
  - Captions E-F (Oversize 1, Folder 4)
  - Captions G-H (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
  - Captions I (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
  - Captions J-M (Oversize 1, Folder 7)
  - Captions N-O (Oversize 1, Folder 8)
  - Captions P-S (Oversize 1, Folder 9)
  - Captions T-V (Oversize 1, Folder 10)
  - Captions W-Y (Oversize 1, Folder 11)
- Biographical material
  - Calendar, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1932-1933; circa 1942-1945,; 1956-1957,; 1966,; undated (Box 1)
  - Commencement program (1966), portrait (1953), stationery (undated) (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - List of correspondence received, 1 Mar 1967; list composed by Lou Erickson upon his donation of materials to Syracuse University. (Box 1)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1954; 1956,; 1962,; 1964,; undated (Box 1)
  - Incoming correspondence, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Newspaper columns written by Erickson, 1963; 1965-1967,; undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper editorials written by Erickson, 1965-1966; undated; most are between 50 and 200 words (Box 1)
  - Daily editorial cartoon collections, 1962; 1964-1965; 12 page booklets of Erickson's cartoons published by the Atlanta Journal (Box 1)
  - The Microphone, 7 Aug 1935; publication from Fort George Wright, Washington, issue #3, edited and illustrated by Erickson during his service in the Civilian Conservation Corps (Box 1)
  - Yale Political, May 1963; contains several cartoons by Erickson (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous- National Newspaper Week promotion, How to Fold a Pressman's Hat, Convenience Store Journal article reprint, Youth magazine (11 Oct 1964), Westinghouse announcement (circa 1959) (Box 1)
  - Promotional material for the Atlantic Traffic and Safety Council, Dec 1966; undated; traffic code booklet, game, handouts, sticker, poster and other illustrations (Oversize 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1961; 1963,; 1965-1966; drawings that appeared in the Atlanta Journal and Atlanta Journal Constitution magazine to illustrate feature stories, the fun page and travel section (Oversize 2)
  - WWII era cartoon clippings, 1944; undated; clippings bearing the signature "Sgt. Erickson" (Oversize 2)
- Miscellaneous drawings
  - Photocopy of "Draw Your Own Conclusions", 2 ink drawings, photocopy of unnamed illustration series, undated (Oversize 2)
  - Georgia Press Association Free Enterprise Promotion Cartoons, 1966 (Oversize 2)
  - Engraver's proof for The Green Berets serialization in the Atlanta Journal, 1966 (Map-case 1, Drawer 100)
  - Untitled ink drawing, undated (Map-case 1, Drawer 100)
Index to cartoons
The following is a list of predominant people, places and subjects appearing in the editorial cartoons in this collection. The list is not exhaustive. Some subjects may appear under and alternative term.
B= Box, F= Folder. For example: B1F1= Box 1 Folder 1.
Africa B1F2
Arnall, Ellis B1F2
Barnett, Ross B1F10
baseball B1F5
Britain B1F2
Byrd, Harry B1F11
capital punishment B1F9
children B1F2
China B1F3-B1F4
Civil Rights B1F2 B1F4 B1F7
Cold War B1F3
Common Market B1F2
communism B1F1 B1F3
Congress B1F2-B1F3 B1F6-B1F7 B1F9-B1F10
Cuba B1F3
de Gaulle, Charles B1F1-B1F2
Democratic Party B1F1-B1F3 B1F5 B1F11
demonstrations B1F4
desegregation B1F3
diplomacy B1F1 B1F11
draft B1F4
driving B1F3 B1F5-B1F7 B1F7
economy B1F4 B1F6
education B1F8-B1F10
elections B1F1-B1F3 B1F5
federal funding B1F3
foreign policy B1F8
France B1F2
free enterprise B1F1
Goldwater, Barry B1F3 B1F8 B1F11
golf B1F7
Great Society B1F7
Harris, Roy B1F9
humanitarianism B1F7
Humphrey, Hubert B1F8
Johnson, Lyndon Baines B1F3-B1F5 B1F7-B1F9 B1F11
journalism B1F5
Korean War B1F7
liberty B1F6-B1F7
Maddox, Lester B1F1-B1F2 B1F6-B1F7 B1F9-B1F11
McNamara, Robert B1F7
Nader, Ralph B1F5
nature B1F9-B1F11
Nazism B1F8
neutrality B1F8
nuclear weapons B1F6 B1F8-B1F9
opera B1F2
politics B1F1 B1F5 B1F8
pollution B1F2-B1F3 B1F6
Pravda B1F1
prices B1F1
privacy B1F11
public service B1F9
Republican Party B1F1 B1F3 B1F8
Rhodesia B1F2
right to work B1F5
Russell, Donald B1F10
Russia B1F3
Sanders, Carl B1F9
school dropouts B1F11
sectionalism B1F5 B1F11
security B1F8
slums B1F6
Soviet Union B1F1
space exploration B1F2
strikes B1F11
Supreme Court B1F3
taxes B1F2 B1F7 B1F9-B1F11
transit B1F6
urban renewal B1F10
Vietnam War B1F3-B1F5 B1F7 B1F10-B1F11
Wallace, George B1F10
Warren Commission B1F2
Weltner, Charles B1F6